Guide to the Jacques Barzun Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XVII: 1991 Gift
  - Correspondence:
    - Miscellaneous, 1981-90 (Box 368)
    - Requests from Publishers, 1989-90 (Box 368)
  - Subject Files:
    - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1987-89 (Box 369)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1984-90 (Box 369)
    - Begin Here, 1990-91 (Box 369)
    - Begin Here, (Uncorrected page proof) (Box 369)
    - A Catalogue of Crime:
      - Correspondence with Reviews and Announcements, 1971-91 (Box 369)
      - Correspondence about the revised edition, Reviews, etc. 1988-89(1) (Box 369)
      - Correspondence about the revised edition. Reviews, etc. 1988-89(2) (Box 369)
      - Correspondence about the revised edition. Reviews, etc. 1988-89(3) (Box 369)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part I, A-Ch (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part I, Cl-Gil (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part I, Gis-Lit (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part I, Liv-Rut (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part I, S --Z (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part II (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part III (Box 370)
      - Revised Edition (t.ms., photocopy) Part IV and V (Box 370)
    - Columbia University, 1960-82 (1) (Box 371)
    - Columbia University, 1960-82 (2) (Box 371)
    - Columbia University, 1989-90 (Box 371)
    - Council for Basic Education, 1989-90 (Box 371)
    - The Culture We Deserve, 1989-90 (Box 371)
    - The Dallas Institute of Humanities and Culture, 1985-91 (Box 371)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1985-90 (Box 371)
    - An Essay on French Verse, 1990-91 (Box 371)
    - Marlboro College International Symposium on the American Experience, 1984-88 (Conference never held) (Box 372)
    - The Modern Researcher, 1986-88 (Box 372)
    - New York: Society Library. 1984-90 (Box 372)
    - Teacher in America-An agreement about usurped rights by University Publishing Associates, 1986-88 (Box 372)
    - University of Texas at San Antonio, 1982-90 (Box 372)
    - A Word or Two Before You Go. 1986-88 (Box 372)
  - Miscellaneous:
    - Address Lists (Box 372)
    - Flaubert., G. Dictionary of Accepted Ideas Errata 1954 ed. (Box 372)
  - Printed Materials:
    - Clippings, Announcements, Invitations. Brochures, etc. with References to Barzun, 1977 1986-90 (Box 372)
    - Books Inscribed to Barzun (1) (Box 372)
    - Books Inscribed to Barzun (2) (Box 373)
- Series XVIII: 1992 Gift
  - Consultant at Scribners', 1973-1991
  - Correspondence, manuscripts, memoranda, & printed materials (Box 374)
  - Writings by Jacques Barzun:
    - Begin here / the forgotten conditions of teaching and learning. Correspondence, memoranda, editorial & printed materials (Box 374)
    - The Modern Researcher. 5th edition. "Master copy and materials for revision" Correspondence, new text & changes, & printed materials (Box 375 & 376)
    - Articles. lectures. & proofs. Typescripts, notes, & misc. (Box 377)
    - Printed copies of books & periodicals with contributions by J.B. (Box 378)
  - Writings by others:
    - Adler, Mortimer J.:
      - A second look in the rearview mirror / further autobiographical reflections of a philosopher at large. Photocopy of typescript & inscribed copy of book (Box 379)
    - Chambrun, Rene de:
      - Ma croisade pour l'Angleterre June 1940. Photocopy of typescript, copies of research materials, & inscribed copy of book (Box 379)
    - Smith, Woodruff:
      - Death of a Fellow. Two typescript drafts (Box 380)
    - Books inscribed to Jacques Barzun (Box 381)
  - Misc. printed materials (Box 381)
  - "Personal documents not reserved":
    - Family history, photographs, & movie film (Box 382)
    - Course outlines & reading lists (Box 382)
    - Two mystery stories by "Bayard Wendell" [Barzun & Taylor] Typescripts (Box 382)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 382)
  - There are also two boxes of family letters and documents shelved with the other restricted containers
- Series XIX: 1993 Gift
  - American Philosophical Society, 1990-92. Correspondence (Box 383)
  - Answers to authors, January -August 1991 (Box 383)
  - Answers to authors, September 1991-December 92 (Box 383)
  - Begin here / the forgotten conditions of teaching and learning. Correspondence, reviews, & advertising, 1991-92 (Box 383)
  - Columbia University. Correspondence, 1991-93 (Box 383)
  - Comments on Jacques Banzun's writings, Correspondence, 1990-92 (Box 384)
  - Education criticism, 1988-1991. Correspondence (Box 384)
  - Engagement calendar, 1987-1988. History and educational associations, 1982-1992. Correspondence (Box 384)
  - Manuscripts by others:
    - Carroll, Dennis: "Double deception". (playscript) Typescript (Box 384)
    - Cornwell, Patricia D.: "Cruel and unusual". (murder mystery). Photocopy of a typescript, 1992 (Box 384)
    - Olson, Ron: "The case o/the Quaker conspiracy / a biographical novel". Typescript of chapter one, 1991 Typescript extracts of later chapters (Box 384)
    - Rollo, David: "Moon over Madrid". (poem) 1993. Typescript (Box 384)
  - Misc. royalties. 1985-1991 (Box 385)
  - The Modern Researcher. 5th edition, 1990-1991 (Box 385)
  - The New York Society Library, 1990-1991 (Box 385)
  - The New York Society Library-Trustees' meetings, 1991-1992 (Box 385)
  - Proofs of books by John Gross & John Lukacs, 1992-1993 (Box 385)
  - Reports to publishers (excluding Scribner's), 1986-1992 (Box 385)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons Publishers, 1988-1992 (Box 385)
  - Printed books:
    - Inscribed by authors to Jacques Barzun (Box 386)
    - Books with notes added (Box 386)
    - Books with references to Jacques Barzun (Box 387)
    - Series edited by Jacques Barzun (Box 387)
    - Series edited by Jacques Barzun (Box 388)
  - Envelope of family letters and documents shelved with the other restricted containers.
    [Closed]
- Series XX: 1994 Gift
  - American Academy for Liberal Education, 1993 (Box 389)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1990-1993 (Box 389)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1992-1994 (Box 389)
  - The American Scholar, 1987-1993 (Box 389)
  - Articles accepted, 1990-1993 (Box 389)
  - Articles rejected, 1989-1993 (Box 389)
  - Berlioz, correspondence about, 1992-1993 (Box 389)
  - Century Association, 1951 1987-1994 (Box 390)
  - Columbia University, 1992-1994 (Box 390)
  - Comments about JB's articles and lectures, 1983-1994 (Box 390)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1991-1993 (Box 390)
  - Criticism, various, 1990-1993 (Box 390)
  - Education, 1992-1994 (Box 390)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1990-1992 (Box 390)
  - Lectures declined, 1990-1992 (Box 390)
  - Manuscripts by others:
    - Reuben, Shelly: Origin & cause. (murder mystery) photocopy (Box 391)
  - Miscellaneous invitations, 1989-1994 (Box 391)
  - New York Society Library, 1993-1994 (Box 391)
  - Recommendations, 1988-1992 (Box 391)
  - St. John's College (Lecture & Columbia Seminar), 1987-1988
  - Scribner's, 1992-1993 (Box 391)
  - To authors, about their books, 1993-1994 (Box 391)
  - To publishers, about their books, 1993-1994 (Box 391)
  - U.S. English, 1979-1993 (Box 391)
  - Writings by Jacques Barzun:
    - The American university. Reissue, 1991-1993 (Box 392)
    - Begin here / the forgotten conditions o/teaching and learning, 1991-1992 (Box 392)
    - The Culture we deserve, 1989-1991 (Box 392)
    - An Essay on French verse/or readers of English poetry, 1991-1992 (Box 392)
    - The Modern Researcher, 5th edition, 1988-1992 (Box 392)
    - Simple and Direct, Reissue, 1979-1993 (Box 392)
    - A Stroll With William James, Correspondence, 1983-1993 & Notebooks (4) (Box 392)
  - Printed books:
    - Inscribed by authors to Jacques Barzun (Box 393)
    - Inscribed by authors to Jacques Barzun (Box 394)
    - With articles by Barzun (Box 394)
    - With references to Barzun (Box 394)
    - Miscellaneous books (Box 394)
- Series XXI: 1995 Gift
  - Chambrun, René de -- re. Pierre Laval, 1991-1994 (Box 395)
  - Columbia University business-various, 1994 (Box 395)
  - Comments on writings, 1994-1995 (Box 395)
  - Correspondence re.The Modern Researcher, 1992-1993 (Box 395)
  - Correspondence with authors, 1994 (Box 395)
  - General critic-questions, 1994-1995 (Box 395)
  - Miller, Charles-photocopies (Box 395)
  - Misc. invitations, 1994-1995 (Box 395)
  - New York Society Library, 1994 (Box 395)
  - On language, 1992-1994 (Box 395)
  - Printed materials: Books inscribed to Jacques Barzun (Box 396)
  - Printed materials: Books re. Barzun with his contributions, etc. (Box 397)
  - Printed materials: Misc. books (Box 398)
  - Misc. book (Box (Oversize))
  - Photograph: American Academy of Arts & Letters, 1995 (Box (Oversize))
- Series XXII: 1996 Gift
  - Correspondence: A-J (Box 399)
  - Correspondence: K-Z (Box 400)
  - Correspondence: Family (restricted) & oversized folder (filed at end of correspondence)
  - About music-Berlioz, Shaw, et al. (Box 401)
  - Academies, Associations, Guild., and other memberships (Box 401)
  - The American Scholar (Box 401)
  - Art and the Individual (Box 401)
  - Articles and letters (Box 402)
  - Articles & notes; Berlioz ... (Box 402)
  - Articles & notes on professionalism (PBK), Judges & their work (Box 402)
  - Articles by JB, correspondence, material used (Box 402)
  - Articles requested (Box 402)
  - Arts (Box 402)
  - Arts (general) (Box 402)
  - Berlioz (Box 403)
  - Bibliography (Box 404)
  - Bookplates (Box 404)
  - Breckinridge lectureship (Box 404)
  - Capital punishment, Material for article on (Box 404)
  - Churchill College, Cambridge and University of Buckingham (Box 404)
  - Claremont (Box 404)
  - Claremont College, Lectureship at, 1971 (Box 404)
  - Claremont lectureship (folder #2) (Box 404)
  - Classics, Notes for (Box 405)
  - Club memberships, JB (Box 405)
  - Columbia, Correspondence with or about (Box 405)
  - Comments about articles & talks (Box 405)
  - Copy-editing (language); Behind the blue pencil (Box 405)
  - Copyright, Correspondence with Viking, Macmillan. etc. about (Box 405)
  - Creativity (Box 405)
  - Criticism (1983), Phil., Politics, Social Sci. & Psych. related to (Box 405)
  - Criticism 1983 used in more than one essay (Box 405)
  - Critics & history, UTSA (Box 406)
  - Culture, current for Dict. (Box 406)
  - Democracy and modem government (Box 406)
  - Detective fiction: A Catalogue of Crime (Box 406)
  - Detective fiction: The literature of true crime (Box 406)
  - Detective fiction: Sherlock Holmes ... (Box 406)
  - Detective fiction: Card files (Box 407)
  - Dictionary items: Scholarship (D.C.) History (OAR) (Box 408)
  - Diderot (Box 408)
  - Education, Material & letters mostly for writings on (Box 408)
  - Education, Selected Documents on (Box 408)
  - Follett:Modern American usage, Material collected for completion & rev. of (Box 408)
  - For energies of art (II) (Box 408)
  - For "Why operaÀ" (Box 408)
  - French verse, Material for essay on (Box 409)
  - Germany, Material for (Box 409)
  - Ghosts (for JS volume) (Box 409)
  - History (Box 409)
  - History-general (Box 409)
  - History and historical criticism, Notes for lectures on (Box 409)
  - History of Science, Projected, (with WHT) and other plans and speech outlines (Box 409)
  - History, written fragments, catalogues ... (Box 410)
  - Invitations to speak or appear (Box 410)
  - James, William, by or about (Box 410)
  - James, William Ms. pp. by JB (Box 410)
  - The Language-articles ... (Box 410)
  - Letters & notes to & from JB mostly art & lit. ... (Box 411)
  - Letters-misc.-short-course (innovation) outlines (Box 411)
  - Lincoln, About (Box 411)
  - Lincoln notes for little book (Box 411)
  - Liszt material for essay (Box 411)
  - Library card files (JB's own library) (I) (Box 412)
  - Library card fles (JB's own library) (2) (Box 413)
  - Lit. crit. & cultural hist., Correspondence and notes about (Box 414)
  - Look it up, check it out, Part of material for (Box 414)
  - Miscellaneous requests and comments including the "special cases" ... (Box 414)
  - The Modern Researcher; material for 4th edition (Box 414)
  - The Modern Researcher notes for revision letters from HFG (Box 414)
  - Modernism, Lecture on (Box 414)
  - Notes: Blue books & notebooks (Box 415)
  - Notes for Beddoes, B. Rush, Burke & Hare, and other articles (Box 415)
  - On education (Box 416)
  - On language (Follett revision & Safire) (Box 416)
  - Paris in 1830 (Box 416)
  - Permissions various (Box 416)
  - Railroad essay-Modem researches (Box 416)
  - Recommendations (Box 416)
  - Relativism (Box 416)
  - Romanticism, dead or a1iveÀ (Box 416)
  - Shakespeare (Box 417)
  - Shaw, G.B. (Box 417)
  - SMU, Material for lectures at. Feb 1979 (Box 417)
  - Speech notes and small pieces (Box 417)
  - The sport of research (Columbia alumni· 1986) (Box 417)
  - Television & the schools (CBE· 1986) (Box 417)
  - Thomson, Randall. memorial notice (Box 417)
  - Thoreau (Box 417)
  - To authors & publishers (Box 417)
  - To, from, and about friends (Box 417)
  - Tocqueville (Box 417)
  - Wesleyan-A word or two before you go. (Box 418)
  - Who's who-obits and notices of people I have known or dealt with (Box 418)
  - Manuscripts by JB:
    - Acad/Institute Ceremonial May 20, 1981 (Box 419)
    - Articles by JB (Box 419)
    - Briefs (Box 419)
    - Central influences on American life (Box 419)
    - The erotic Bernard Shaw (Box 419)
    - Essays (Box 419)
    - How the Romantics invented Shakespeare (Box 419)
    - Longer pieces (Box 419)
    - Margaret Mills memorial tribute ... 1993 (Box 419)
    - Minor articles and speeches (Box 419)
    - Our distortion of the 19th century (Box 420)
    - The pleasures and uses of history (Box 420)
    - Speeches and short papers (Box 420)
    - Speeches and short papers, 1947-1995 (Box 420)
    - Talks various (Box 420)
    - When the Orient was new; Byron, Kinglake & Flaubert (Box 420)
    - Why do the arts attack societyÀ (Box 420)
    - Why is modem literature so difficultÀ (Box 420)
    - Written fragments, not used (Box 420)
  - Printed materials:
    - Published articles by JB: A-B(I) (Box 421)
    - Published articles by JB: B(2)-C (Box 422)
    - Published articles by JB: D-L (Box 423)
    - Published articles by JB: M-O (Box 424)
    - Published articles by JB: P-Z (Box 425)
    - Published articles by JB: Unsorted (Box 426)
    - Books by Barzun (2 boxes) (Box 427 & 428)
    - Books with m's contributions & misc. (Box 429)
    - Books with m's annotations (2 boxes) (Box 430 & 431)
    - Books inscribed to 18 (6 boxes) (Box 432-437)
    - Books & off-prints inscribed to JB (Box 438)
  - Tape cassettes (1 box) (Box 439)
- Series XXIII: 2000 Gift
  - American Academy for Liberal Education, 1994-1999 (Box 440)
  - Berlioz and Music, 1995-1998 (Inscribed music scores & tape cassettes by other musicians, 1975-1986 & n.d.) (Box 440)
  - Columbia University, 1996-1999 (Box 440)
  - Critic (General), 1996-1998 (Box 440)
  - Letters received about 90th birthday, 1997-1998 (Box 441)
  - Memberships in associations, 1996-1999 (Box 441)
  - Reviews and Comments, 1996-1998 (Box 441)
  - Steeves, Edna L. & Harrison Ross Steeves: "The Landmarks of Classic Feminism". Typescript, 492p. (Box 441)
  - Music score by Richard Franko Goldman. (inscribed to Barzun & signed by Goldman) (Folder (Oversize))
- Series XXIV: 2001 Gift
  - Columbia University, 1999-2000 (Box 442)
  - From Dawn to Decadence, 1996-2000 (Box 442)
  - From Dawn to Decadence (after publication), 2000 (Box 442)
  - Friends, 1999-2000 (Box 443)
  - Music (mostly Berlioz), 1998-2000 (Box 443)
- Series XXV: Gift of Virginia Xanthos, 1975
  - Scrapbooks about Jacques Barzun:
    - 1. Genera1 clippings, 1925-39 (Box 444)
    - 2. Clippings about race and discrimination (Box 444)
    - 3. Race, The French Race, Of Human Freedom, Darwin Marx Wagner, Romanticism and the Modern Ego (Box 444)
    - 4.Teacher in America, The College Program in Action (Box 445)
    - 5. Berlioz and the Romantic Century, Clippings about Berlioz (to 1956) (Box 446)
    - 5. Clippings about Berlioz (from 1956), Evenings with the Orchestra, Romanticism and the Modern Ego (Box 445)
    - 7. New Letters of Berlioz, Pleasures of Music (Box 445)
    - 8. The Later Ego, Letters of Lord Byron, Dictionary of Accepted Ideas, Darwin Marx Wagner, John Jay Chapman (Box 446)
    - 9.The Energies of Art, Music in American Life, The Modern Researcher (Box 446)
    - 10. The House of Intellect (Box 447)
    - 11.Delights of Detection, Classic Romantic and Modern, Figaro’s Marriage, Science: The G1orious Entertainment (Box 447)
    - 12. Clippings about J.B., 1939 to 1956 God's Country and Mine (Box 448)
    - 12a. Publishers catalogues, etc. about J.B. ca.l946-l950 (in bound book) (Box 447)
    - 13. Clippings about J.B., 1956-58 (Box 448)
    - 14. Clippings about J.B., 1959-61 (Box 449)
    - 15. Clippings about J.B., 1962-1964 (May ) (Box 449)
    - 16. Reviews of works translated into foreign languages (Box 450)
    - 17. Clippings about J.B., 1964 (June )-1965 (Box 450)
    - 18. Clippings about J.B., 1966 (Box 450)
    - 19. Clippings about J.B., 1967 and 1968 (Box 451)
    - 20. Wilson Follett's Modem American Usage (Box 451)
    - 21. The American University (Box 452)
    - 22. Berlioz and the Romantic Century, Third Edit1on; Evenings with the Orchestra, paperback edition (Box 452)
    - 23. A Catalogue of Crime (Box 452)
    - 24. On Writing, Editing, and Publishing: Clio and the Doctors: The Use and Abuse of Art (Box 452)
    - 25. Clippings about J. B., 1969 and 1970 (Box 453)
    - 26. Clipp1ngs about J.B., 1971 1972 & 1973 (Box 453)
    - 27. Clippings about J.B., 1974 & 1975 (Box 453)
- Series XXVI: Tape Recordings:
  - Two Utopias: Mark Van Doren-Tom Lawson-Jacques Barzun, 30 August 1942 (Box 196-197)
  - Descartes, Discourse on the method: Bertrand Russell-Jacques Barzun-Mark Van Doren, 30 August 1942 (Box 196-197)
  - An evening at the Century, 1 May 1958 (Box 196-197)
  - The Cubist decade: then and now, 1 November 1964 (Box 196-197)
  - Barzun speech. (2 tapes), 17 July 1965 (Box 196-197)
  - Mr. Jacques Barzun, 24 /010/1968 (Box 196-197)
  - For art's sake-WCBS "Music til dawn". (2 tapes), 8 March1969 (Box 196-197)
  - Discussion/Interview on College Administration between Jacques Barzun and Dennis Binning of College & University Business Magazine, 9 April 1969 (Box 196-197)
  - National Library Week Luncheon, 21 April 1969 (Box 196-197)
  - Barzun lecture, 29 January 1973 (Box 196-197)
  - The care and feeding of the mind. (2 tapes) (Box 196-197)
  - History for pleasure: a self-justifying sport (2 tapes) (Box 196-197)
  - Insight: the American University-Jacques Barzun, James Hester, George Eisenberger (moderator)-WKCR-FM (Box 196-197)
  - Metropolitan Opera broadcast (Box 196-197)
  - Present-day thoughts on the quality of 11te. (2 tapes) (Box 196-197)
  - Radio Forum-20th Century American (Box 196-197)
  - Misc., The campus library. Religion series. God, basic conceptions (Box 196-197)
  - Preliminary dialogue: McLuhan-Parker (Box 196-197)
  - Record: Wigman, Mary. Tanzerlebnis -- Tanzgestaltunq (Box 196-197)
- Series XXVII: Microfilms
  - Books by Barzun:
    - The American university & Music in American life (Box 198)
    - Classic, Romantic, and Modern (Box 198)
    - Clio and the doctors (Box 198)
    - Delights of detection (Box 198)
    - Darwin, Marx, Wagner (Box 198)
    - Energies of art (Box 198)
    - God’s country and mine (Box 198)
    - The House of Intellect (Box 198)
    - Of Human Freedom (Box 198)
    - On writing, editing, and publishing (Box 198)
    - Pleasures of music (Box 198)
    - Race: a study in superstition (Box 198)
    - Science: the glorious entertainmenmt (Box 198)
    - The selected letters of Lord Byron (Box 199)
    - The selected writings of John Jay Chapman (Box 199)
    - Teacher in America (Box 199)
  - Translations by Barzun:
    - BeauMarchais’s Figaro’s marriage (2 copies) (Box 199)
    - Becque's La Parisienne (Box 199)
    - Courteline’s A rule is a rule (Box 199)
    - Diderot’s Rameau’s nephew (Box 199)
    - Gustave Flaubert’s The dictionary of accepted ideas (Box 199)
    - Mirbeau’s The epidemic (Box 199)
    - Husset’s A door should be either open or shut (Box 199)
    - Musset’s Fantasio (Box 199)
  - Periodicals with Contributions by Barzun:
    - The griffin (Box 199)
    - The mid-century (Box 199)
  - Modern Music Scores:
    - Edward Ballantine (Box 200)
    - Altredo Casella (Box 200)
    - Erik Chisholm (Box 200)
    - G. Dinicu & Jascha Heifetz (Box 200)
    - Gabriel Faure (Box 200)
    - Richard Franko Goldman (Box 200)
    - Patrick Hadley (Box 200)
    - Clayton Johns (Box 200)
    - Darius Milhaud (Box 200)
    - Florent Schmitt (Box 200)
    - Robert Schumann (Box 200)
    - Aleksandr Nikolayevich Scriabin (Box 200)
    - Bruce Simonds (Box 200)
    - Edgard Varsee (Box 200)
    - Peter Warlock & Joseph Szigeti (Box 200)
    - Koscak Yamada (Box 200)
    - Béla Bartók (2) (Box 236)
    - Giles Farnaby (Box 236)
    - Richard Franko Goldman (Box 236)
    - Arthur Honegger (Box 236)
    - G. Francesco Malipiero (Box 236)
    - Bohuslav Martinu (Box 236)
    - Darius Milhaud (Box 236)
    - Quincy Porter (2} (Box 236)
    - Alexander Tscherepnin (Box 236)
- Series XXVIII: Additions to the Collection
  - Barzun, Jacques to Christopher Faille, 1985-1992 (30 t.l.s.) (Box 454)
    Gift of Christopher Faille, 2012